<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Guides on Our lab website</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/guide/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Guides on Our lab website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 14:12:00 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/guide/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Lab Values &amp; Policies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/guide/general/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 12:56:33 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/guide/general/</guid>
      <description>This is a living document and all lab members are encouraged to propose changes as they see fit. It is the entire labs&amp;rsquo; responsibility to hold me accountable to what is written here and I always invite criticism should I fail to comply.&#xA;Overview My main function is to provide a safe, productive, supportive, and, hopefully, fun environment for you to carry out and publish high-quality research. Academia can be full of highs and lows and I will dedicate myself to amplify the highs and buffer the lows as much as possible.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diversity, Equity &amp; Inclusion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/guide/dei/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 14:12:00 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/guide/dei/</guid>
      <description>Overview We value and honor the uniqueness of each individual and embrace diverse backgrounds and viewpoints. We aim to prepare students, postdocs, and visiting scholars for their future as scientists and citizens in an equitable, inclusive, multicultural society.&#xA;Values Our lab holds diversity, equity, and inclusion as core values and is committed to upholding them. Dimensions of diversity include, but are not limited to, race, ethnicity, sexuality, gender identity, socioeconomic background, national or cultural origins, religion, political beliefs, different abilities, neurodiversity, and lifestyle.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The lab wiki</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/guide/wiki/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 14:12:00 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/guide/wiki/</guid>
      <description>A lot of the know-how and ins-and-outs of the lab are kept on our lab wiki which all group members can contribute to.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
